我们已经了解了查询语言的使用方式
PROFESSOR: All right, well, we've seen how the query language works.
现在该来讨论如何实现了
Now, let's talk about how it's implemented.
你们也应该能够想象到
You already pretty much can guess
它其中的原理
what's going on there.
它的最底层是一个模式匹配器
At the bottom of it, there's a pattern matcher.
我们在《基于规则的控制语言》一课中
And we looked at a pattern matcher
已经介绍过模式匹配器了
when we did the rule-based control language.
为了让你们回想起来 我举个例子
Just to remind you, here are some sample patterns.
这个模式会匹配
This is a pattern that will match
一个含有三个元素的表
any list of three things
其中 首元素为'A
which the first is a
其次是'C
the second is c
而中间可以为任意元素
and the middle one can be anything.
所以在这个小型的模式匹配语言中
So in this little pattern-matching syntax,
你只能区分一种类型
there's only one distinction you make.
也就是区分字面量或者变量
There's either literal things or variables,
以问号开头的就是变量
and variables begin with question mark.
因此这个模式会匹配任意的三元表
So this matches any list of three things
只要它的首元素为'A 而第三个元素为'C
of which the first is a and the second is c.
而这个模式匹配的三元表
This one matches any list of three things
它的首元素必须是符号'JOB
of which the first is the symbol job.
第二个元素为任意值
The second can be anything.
第三个元素必须是一个二元表
And the third is a list of two things
二元表的首元素为符号'COMPUTER
of which the first is the symbol computer
第二个元素可以为任意值
and the second can be anything.
而下一条模式所匹配的三元表
And this one, this next one matches any list of three things,
区别就在于
and the only difference is,
在于第三个元素的首元素必须为符号'COMPUTER
here, the third list, the first is the symbol computer,
表剩余部分可以是任意值
and then there's some rest of the list.
也就是说 上面是二元表 而下面没有限定数目
So this means two elements and this means arbitrary number.
然而我们的语言实现
And our language implementation isn't
根本不用操心如何去实现这个点号
isn't even going to have to worry about implementing this dot
因为这个由Lisp读取器自动地完成
because that's automatically done by Lisp's reader.
要注意 匹配器还要保持一致性
Remember matchers also have some consistency in them.
这个模式匹配一个三元表
This match is a list of three things
表的首元素是'A
of which the first is a.
而第二个元素和第三个元素可以是任意值
And the second and third can be anything,
但它们必须是相同的
but they have to be the same thing.
它们都是?X
They're both called x.
而这个模式匹配一个四元表
And this matches a list of four things
其中第一个元素与第四个元素相同
of which the first is the fourth
而第二个元素与第三个元素相同
and the second is the same as the third.
最后一个模式匹配以'A开头的任意表
And this last one matches any list that begins with a.
以'A开头
The first thing is a,
余下的可以是任意值
and the rest can be anything.
这是对我们已经学习过的模式匹配语言
So that's just a review of pattern matcher syntax
的一个回顾
that you've already seen.
还记得吗
And remember,
这是由一个叫做MATCH的过程实现的
that's implemented by some procedure called match.
MATCH有三个参数：PATTERN、DATA以及DICTIONARY
And match takes a pattern and some data and a dictionary.
MATCH考虑的是
And match asks the question
利用给定DICTIONAY中的绑定
is there any way to match this pattern against this data object
能够找到一种方法把模式与数据对象匹配起来吗？
subject to the bindings that are already in this dictionary?
比如说
So, for instance,
如果我们想要把模式(?X ?Y ?Y ?X)
if we're going to match the pattern x, y, y, x
与数据对象(A B B A)相匹配
against the data a, b, b, a
又给定了一个字典 X=A
subject to a dictionary, that says x equals a.
MATCH就会说：“它们是一致的”
Then the matcher would say, yes, that's consistent.
再给定的字典说 X=A 的情况下
These match, and it's consistent
模式与数据相匹配
with what's in the dictionary to say that x equals a.
而匹配的结果则是
And the result of the match
一个扩展了的词典
is the extended dictionary
其中包含 X=A Y=B
that says x equals a and y equals b.
MATCH接收PAT、DATA和DICTIONAY
So a matcher takes in pattern data dictionary,
如果成功匹配就输出一个扩展后的词典
puts out an extended dictionary if it matches,
否则就报错
or if it doesn't match, says that it fails.
因此 比如说
So, for example,
如果我在这里使用同样的模式
if I use the same pattern here,
如果我用模式(?X ?Y ?Y ?X)
if I say this x, y, y, x
去匹配(A B B A)
match a, b, b, a
并给定词典 Y=A
with the dictionary y equals a,
那么MATCH就会输出FAIL
then the matcher would put out fail.
由于我们已经降解过模式匹配器的代码了
Well, you've already seen the code for a pattern matcher
我就不会再去细讲
so I'm not going to go over it,
这跟我们以前做的类似
but it's the same thing we've been doing before.
我们在《基于规则的系统》中已经见过了
You saw that in the system on rule-based control.
基本上是同样的匹配器
It's essentially the same matcher.
实际上 我认为这里的语法还更简单一点
In fact, I think the syntax is a little bit simpler
因为我们不用去关心
because we're not worrying about
任意变量、任意表达式之类的东西
arbitrary constants and expressions and things.
这里面只区分变量和常量
There's just variables and constants.
那么 有了模式匹配器以后
OK, well, given that,
基本查询又是怎么样的呢？
what's a primitive query?
基本查询将会是一个相当复杂的东西
Primitive query is going to be a rather complicated thing.
就拿查询(JOB ?X (?D . y))来说
It's going to be-- let's think about the query job of x is d dot y.
我们可能会输入这样的查询
That's a query we might type in.
这又将如何在系统内实现呢？
That's going to be implemented in the system.
我们可以把它想做这个小盒子
We'll think of it as this little box.
这是一条基本查询
Here's the primitive query.
这个小盒子将会
What this little box is going to do
以两条流作为输入
is take in two streams and put out a stream.
并输出一条流
and put out a stream.
因此一条基本查询的形状
So the shape of a primitive query
就将是有两条输入流
is that it's a thing where two streams come in
和一条输出流
and one stream goes out.
而这些流 来自于这里的数据库
What these streams are going to be is down here is the database.
因此我们把数据库中的所有数据
So we imagine all the things in the database
想象成一条流
sort of sitting there in a stream
而这个盒子不断地吸取
and this thing sucks on them.
那么 数据库中有什么呢？
So what are some things that might be in the database?
首先是(JOB (ALYSSA ...))
Oh, job of Alyssa is something
以及还有其它的JOB数据
and some other job is something.
想象一下 数据库中的所有事实都在这条流中
So imagine all of the facts in the database sitting there in the stream.
都到了这里
That's what comes in here.
而这条流送来的 是一些字典
What comes in here is a stream of dictionaries.
其中一个就可能是
So one particular dictionary might say
Y=PROG
might say y equals programmer.
现在 查询工作就是要
Now, what the query does
当它从这条流中取得一个字典后
when it gets in a dictionary from this stream,
它会搜寻数据库中的东西
it finds all possible ways of matching the query
尽可能产生所有匹配结果
against whatever is coming in from the database.
它把查询视作一种模式
It looks at the query as a pattern,
并将它们与数据库中的事实匹配起来
matches it against any fact from the database
结合着相应的字典中的数据
or all possible ways of finding and matching the database
找到数据库中所有匹配的结果
with respect to this dictionary that's coming in.
所以针对数据库中的每条事实
So for each fact in the database,
它都会调用(MATCH PAT FACT DICTIONAY)来检查
it calls the matcher using the pattern, fact, and dictionary.
如果成功匹配
And every time it gets a good match,
它就输出一个扩展了的字典
it puts out the extended dictionary.
比如说 这里进来了一本字典
So, for example, if this one comes in
并且成功匹配
and it finds a match,
那么就会输出一本字典
out will come a dictionary
本例中就是Y=PROGRAMER
that in this case will have y equals programmer
X=...
nd x equals something.
Y=PROGRAMMER X=...
y is programmer, x is something,
D又是一个新的项
and d is whatever it found.
像这样扩展
And that's all.
当然 它会针对数据库中的所有事实做同样的尝试
And, of course, it's going to try this for every fact in the dictionary.
所以就可能有很多的结果
So it might find lots of them.
可能会产生另一本字典
It might find another one
其中 Y=PROGRAMMER X=... D=...
that says y equals programmer and x equals, and d equals.
因此 对于每个输入的框架
So thats, So for one frame coming in,
对于每输入一本字典
it might put out-- for one dictionary coming in,
它可能输出很多本字典
it might put out a lot of dictionaries,
或者什么也不输出
or it might put out none.
可能会有一些不匹配的情况 比如X=FOO
It might have something that wouldn't match like x equals FOO.
这个条目不会匹配任何东西
This one might not match anything
就这个框架来说 不会向输出流中输出东西
in which case nothing will go into this stream corresponding to this frame.
或者你也可以输入一个空框架
Or what you might do is put in an empty frame,
空框架是用来
and an empty frame says try matching all ways--
在没有任何约束的情况下
find all possible ways of matching the query
匹配数据库中所有可能的结果
against something in the database subject to no previous restrictions.
这仅仅代表着
And if you think about what that means, that's just
处理你输入的查询 最初所进行的计算
the computation that's done when you type in a query right off.
它试图找出所有的匹配
It tries to find all matches.
基本查询建立了这种机制
So a primitive query sets up this mechanism.
而语言要做的是
And what the language does,
当你在顶层输入这条查询时
when you type in the query at the top level,
它基于这种机制
it takes this mechanism,
它会输入一本空的字典
feeds in one single empty dictionary,
而对于输出的每个东西
and then for each thing that comes out
然后把最初的查询
takes the original query
用不用的字典来实例化
and instantiates the result with all the different dictionaries,
于是实例化后的模式就形成了一条新的流
producing a new stream of instantiated patterns here.
这就是在终端上打印出来的内容
And that's what gets printed on the terminal.
这也就是其中的基本原理
That's the basic mechanism going on there.
那么 这又为什么复杂呢？
Well, why is that so complicated?
当让 除了用这种遍布四处的基于流的方法
You probably can think of a lot simpler ways to arrange this match for
你们可以想出很多更简单的方法来组织基本查询
a primitive query rather than having all of these streams floating around.
而答案就在于
And the answer is--
你们可能已经在想了
you probably guess already.
答案就是 这种方法能够优雅地
The answer is this thing extends elegantly
实现组合的方法
to implement the means of combination.
比如说
So, for instance,
假设我还想实现其它的效果
suppose I don't only want to do this.
我不只是想查询所有人的工作信心
I don't want to say who to be everybody's job description.
假设我还想查询
Suppose I want to say
(AND (JOB ?X (?D . ?Y))
to say AND the job of x is d dot y
(SUPERVIOSR ?X ?Z))
and the supervisor of x is z.
(SUPERVISOR ?X ?Z)这条查询
Now, supervisor of x is z
是另外的一条基本查询
is going to be another primitive query
它也有类似的形状——接收一条数据对象流
that has the same shape to take in a stream of data objects,
一条初始字典流
a stream of initial dictionaries,
字典是你在进行匹配时 需要遵循的约束
which are the restrictions to try and use when you match,
然后它会输出一条字典流
and it's going to put out a stream of dictionaries.
这就是这条基本查询的形状
So that's what this primitive query looks like.
我又该如何实现AND呢？
And how do I implement the AND?
其实很简单
Well, it's simple.
把它们连接起来就好了
I just hook them together.
我把这条查询的输出
I take the output of this one,
连接在这条查询的输入上
and I put that to the input of that one.
然后把这里的字典扇出开来
And I take the dictionary here and I fan it out.
你们就能发现它是如何工作的了
And then you see how that's going to work,
这里会输出一个框架
because what's going to happen is a frame will now come in here,
其中有X、Y和D的绑定
which has a binding for x, y, and d.
当后面的查询接收到结果后
And then when this one gets it, it'll say,
当它了解了这些约束后
oh, gee, subject to these restrictions,
字典中的是Y、X和D的值
which now already have values in the dictionary for y and x and d,
它会搜寻数据库
it looks in the database and says,
试图找到有关SUPERVISOR关系的事实
gee, can I find any supervisor facts?
如果找到了的话 它就会输出一些词典
And if it finds any, out will come dictionaries
其中有Y、X、D以及Z的绑定
which have bindings for y and x and d and z now.
不过要注意
And then notice that the match---
因为这里输入的框架建立了约束
because the frames coming in here have these restrictions,
它保证了当你执行AND运算时
that's the thing that assures when you do the AND,
这两个X是相同的
this x will mean the same thing as that x.
这是因为通过这条流输出时
Because by the time something comes floating in here,
X已经有值了 你要确保匹配的一致性
x has a value that you have to match against consistently.
然后我们想起在MATCH的代码中
And then you remember from the code from the matcher,
有一种操作字典的特殊组织方法
there was something in the way the matcher did dictionaries
确保了匹配的一致性
that arrange consistent matches.
这就是AND的实现
So there's AND.
关键是要注意它的一般性形状
The important point to notice is the general shape.
我们来看看(AND P Q)
Look at what happened: the AND of two queries, say, P and Q.
这里是P和Q
Here's P and Q.
两条查询的AND
The AND of two queries,
看起来像是这样
well, it looks like this.
每一条查询都通过一条流连接数据库
Each query takes in a stream from the database,
一条输入流
a stream of inputs,
并输出一条输出流
and puts out a stream of outputs.
关键是要注意
And the important point to notice
如果我在它们周围画一个盒子
is that if I draw a box around this thing
这就是(AND P Q)
and say this is AND of P and Q,
那么这个盒子也有同样的形状
then that box has exactly the same overall shape.
它也有一条连接数据库的流
It's something that takes in a stream from the database.
但是在内部会扇出开来
Here it's going to get fanned out inside,
但是在外部你看不到
but from the outside you don't see that.
它接收一个流 并输出一个流
It takes an input stream and puts out an output stream.
这就是AND
So this is AND.
类似地 OR可能看起像这样
And then similarly, OR would look like this.
虽然我没给你们演示过OR的用法
OR would-- although I didn't show you examples of OR.
OR会尝试找出P或Q所有匹配的事实
OR would say can I find all ways of matching P or Q.
P、Q两条查询都有各自的形状
So I have P and Q. Each will have their shape.
OR的实现则是
And the way OR is implemented is
我把来自于数据库的流
I'll take my database stream.
扇出开来
I'll fan it out.
把它们分别送给P和Q
I'll put one into P and one into Q.
我把最初的查询流也给扇出开来
I'll take my initial query stream coming in and fan it out.
这样我不但能够得到P的所有结果
So I'll look at all the answers I might get from P
也能得到Q的所有结果
and all the answers I might get from Q,
把这些输出送入某种“附加器”中
and I'll put them through some sort of thing that appends them
或者把它们“合并”到一条流中
or merges the result into one stream,
然后得到输出
and that's what will come out.
而从外部来看 这整个东西就是OR
And this whole thing from the outside is OR.
同样的 当你们从外部观察它时
And again, you see it has the same overall shape
你会发现它具有相同的形状
NOT又如何实现呢？
What's NOT?
NOT的原理有些类似
NOT works kind of the same way.
如果我有一条查询P
If I have some query P,
这是一条基本查询P
If I have P, I take the primitive query for P.
现在我要实现(NOT P)
Here, I'm going to implement NOT P.
NOT的作用像是一个过滤器
And NOT's just going to act as a filter.
这里连接数据库
I'll take in the database
这里是输入的字典流
and my original stream of dictionaries coming in,
(NOT P)要做的就是
and what NOT P will do is
对这些东西做过滤
it will filter these guys.
过滤的方法则是
And the way it will filter it,
如果我在这里获得了一本字典
it will say when I get in a dictionary here,
那么我就去找所有的匹配
I'll find all the matches,
然后丢弃找到的结果
and if I find any, I'll throw it away.
如果我没有在这里找到匹配
And if I don't find any matches to something coming in here,
我就把它传递过去
I'll just pass that through,
NOT就是一个纯粹的过滤器
so NOT is a pure filter.
因此AND就类似于一个电阻
So AND is-- think of these sort of electoral resistors or something.
AND是串行的组合
AND is series combination
OR是并行组合
and OR is parallel combination.
然而NOT并不会对字典做任何扩展
And then NOT is not going to extend any dictionaries at all.
它只会做过滤
It's just going to filter it.
它会丢弃那些能够匹配的结果
It's going to throw away the ones for which it finds a way to match.
LISP-VALUE的原理类似
And lisp-value is sort of the same way.
它的过滤器会复杂点
The filter's a little more complicated.
因为要应用到谓词上
It applies to predicate.
这里需要注意的关键点是
The major point to notice here,
我们之前也强调过了
and it's a major point we've looked at before,
就是关于“闭包性质”的思想
is this idea of closure.
我们通过组合手段构建的东西
The things that we build as a means of combination
跟所使用的基本物件
have the same overall structure
有同样的结构
as the primitive things that we're combining.
所以从外面看
So the AND of two things
查询的AND与基本查询结构相同
looked at from the outside has the same shape.
这就意味着
And what that means is that
这里的盒子可以是AND、OR、NOT或者其它的
this box here could be an AND or an OR or a NOT or something
因为它具有相同的形状来连接更大的东西
because it has the same shape to interface to the larger things.
这种思想能够让我们获得
It's the same thing that allowed us to get
Escher绘图语言中的那种复杂度
complexity in the Escher picture language
让你能够仅仅使用序对
or allows you to immediately build up these
构建出这些复杂结构
complicated structures just out of pairs.
这就是“闭包性质”
It's closure.
这种性质
And that's the thing that
能够让我完成你们现在觉得理所当然的事儿
allowed me to do what by now you took for granted
比如我可以查询(AND JOB SALARY)
I said, gee, there's a query which is AND of job and salary,
当然我也可以查询(AND JOB (NOT ...))等等
and I said, oh, there's another one, which is AND of job, a NOT of something.
这种便利是由
The fact that I can do that is
这种“闭包原则”直接带给我们的
a direct consequence of this closure principle.
好吧 提问时间
OK, let's break and then we'll go on.
学生：字典是从哪里来的？
AUDIENCE: Where does the dictionary come from?
教授：字典最初来自于你的输入
PROFESSOR: The dictionary comes initially from what you type in.
因此当你最初进行查询时
So when you start this up,
它首先会建立起这整个结构
the first thing it does is set up this whole structure.
它先输入一个空字典
It puts in one empty dictionary.
如果你只有一条基本查询的话
And if all you have is one primitive query,
那么它就会输出一系列具有内容的字典
then what will come out is a bunch of dictionaries with things filled in.
这里演示的一般性情况是
The general situation that I have here
某个嵌套组合查询的中间过程
is when this is in the middle of some nest of combined things.
所以在那时
So by the time.
让我们来看看这里
Let's look at the picture over here.
这条SUPERVISOR查询得到了某本字典
This supervisor query gets in some dictionary.
这本字典来自于哪里呢？
Where did this one come from?
它来自于
This dictionary came from the fact that
这条基本查询的输出
I'm looking at the output of this primitive query.
说得更具体一点
So maybe to be very specific,
如果我最初在顶层只输入了这条查询
if I literally typed in just this query at the top level,
这整条AND查询
this AND,
它实际上会构建这种结构
what would actually happen is it would build this structure
并使用一本空字典来启动整个过程
and start up this whole thing with one empty dictionary.
处理过程开始后 会产生一系列的字典
And now this one would process, and a whole bunch of dictionaries
其中就有X、Y以及D
would come out with x, y's and d's in them.
向这边传递
Run it through this one.
这就是这条查询的输入
So now that's the input to this one.
这条查询也会生成其它的东西
This one would now put out some other stuff.
如果这整个查询是构建在一个更大的查询中的话
And if this itself were buried in some larger thing,
比如说一条OR查询
like an OR of something,
那么它将输出到下一个查询中
then that would go feed into the next one.
因此最初开始处理时 只有一本空字典
So you initially get only one empty dictionary when you start it,
但是在处理这些复合查询的过程中
but as you're in the middle of processing these compounds things,
会生成各种不同的字典
that's where these cascades of dictionaries start getting generated.
学生：字典都是查询的结果吗？
AUDIENCE: Dictionaries only come about as a result of using the queries?
它们会变成
Or do they stays, do they become--
它们存储在数据库中吗？
do they stay someplace in space like the database does?
它们是临时数据吗？
Are these temporary items?
它们是在匹配过程中临时创建的
PROFESSOR: They're created temporarily in the matcher.
但它们实际存放在内存中
Really, they're someplace in storage.
最初 某人创建了一本THE-EMPTY-DICT字典
Initially, someone creates a thing called the empty dictionary
送入这个匹配过程
that gets initially fed to this match procedure,
MATCH过程据此构建新字典
and then the match procedure builds some dictionaries,
并把它们传递下去
and they get passed on and on.
学生：因此匹配完成后它们就被丢弃了？
AUDIENCE: OK, so they'll go way after the match?
教授：实际上 当没人需要它们后就被废料回收了
PROFESSOR: They'll go away when no one needs them again, yeah.
学生：似乎AND查询对数据库进行了冗余操作
AUDIENCE: It appears that the AND performs some redundant searches of the database.
如果第一条子句扫描过了
If the first clause matched,
比如说前两个元素没有匹配 而第三个元素匹配了
let's say, the third element and not on the first two elements,
然而第二条子句又会检查这两个元素
the second clause is going to look at those first two elements again,
然后又一次丢弃这些不匹配的元素
discarding them because they don't match.
而字典中已经有匹配的项了
The match is already in the dictionary.
如果我们把数据库中的数据
Would it makes sense to carry the data element
也放到字典中 这样可行么？
from the database along with the dictionary?
教授：实际上 通常来说
PROFESSOR: Yeah, there're... Well, in general,
我们能够以其它方式来安排这些搜索
there are other ways to arrange this search,
你也可以做一些分析
and there's some analysis that you can do.
我记得书里面就有这样的习题
I think there's a problem in the book,
是考察通过安排AND子句的顺序
which talks about a different way that you can cascade AND
来消除不同类型的冗余
to eliminate various kinds of redundancies.
而这里只是为了
This one is meant to be--
用非常简单的情况来向你们展示它们是如何配合的
was mainly meant to be very simple so you can see how they fit together.
但是你说得非常对
But you're quite right.
这些冗余是可以避免的
There are redundancies here that you can get rid of.
这也是这门语言缓慢的原因之一
That's another reason why this language is somewhat slow.
你们可以让它变得更聪明
There are a lot smarter things you can do.
我只是为了向你们演示非常简单的、原理性的实现
We're just trying to show you a very simple, in principle, implementation.
学生：您是根据Prolog来建模这门语言的
AUDIENCE: Did you model this language on Prolog,
还是说它只是偶然地像Prolog？
or did it just come out looking like Prolog?
教授：Gerry教授昨天羞辱了一大堆人
PROFESSOR: Well, Gerry insulted a whole bunch of people yesterday,
我想说真实的情况是
so I might as well say that the MIT attitude towards Prolog is
MIT的研究人员在1971年做了类似的事
is something that people did in about 1971
但是发现这个方向并不正确 并停止了研究
and decided that it wasn't really the right thing and stopped.
因此我们是根据查询处理的基本原理建模的
So we modeled this on the sort of natural way that this thing was done
大概在1971年左右
in about 1971,
只是说 那时候我们还没有用流来实现
except at that point, we didn't do it with streams.
然后我们 -- 但我们使用了它差不多六个月后
And then we... After we were using it for about six months,
发现它存在各种各样的问题
we discovered that it had all these problems,
稍后我会解释
some of which I'll talk about later.
然后我们就想
And we said,
Prolog一定解决了这些问题
gee, Prolog must have fixed those,
但却发现它并没有
and then we found out that it didn't.
从这种意义上来说 它确实跟Prolog一样
So this does about the same thing as Prolog.
学生：Prolog基于流么？
AUDIENCE: Does Prolog use streams?
教授：不 Prolog基于的是
PROFESSOR: No. Prolog --
就行为上来说 我们的语言很像Prolog
In how it behaves, it behaves a lot like Prolog.
Prolog使用回溯策略
Prolog uses a backtracking strategy.
但是Prolog有一个优点非常好
But the other thing that's really good about Prolog
也使得它变得实用
that makes it a usable thing
你知道吗
is that there's a really very, very
它们精心设计了Prolog的编译器
there's a really very, very well-engineered compiler technology
使得它能够高速运行
that makes it run fast.
因此 虽然我们这门语言非常缓慢地输出答案
So although you saw the merge spitting out these answers very, very slowly,
真正的Prolog程序却运行得非常快
a real Prolog will run very, very fast.
这是因为 尽管搜索过程十分低效
Because even though it's sort of doing this,
Prolog卓越的编译器也会高校地完成工作
the real work that went into Prolog is a very, very excellent compiler effort.
休息一下吧
Let's take a break.
我们已经考察过了基本查询
We've looked at the primitive queries
以及如何使用流来实现组合的手段
and the ways that streams are used to implement the means of combination:
AND、OR以及NOT
AND and OR and NOT.
现在 该讨论抽象的手段了
Now, let go on to the means of abstraction.
回想一下 我们这门语言的抽象手段是RULE
Remember, the means of abstraction in this language are rules.
(BOSS ?Z ?D)描述的是
So z is a boss in division d
如果某人在D部门工作
if there's some x who has a job in division d
并且Z是X的上司
and z is the supervisor of x.
这就是所谓的“BOSS”
That's what it means for someone to be a boss.
并且 实际上
So, and in effect,
如果我们考察一下编写的规则与这边的关系
if you think about what we're doing with relation to this,
这是我们编写的查询
there's the query we wrote--
这个是(JOB ?X ?D) 而这个是(SUPERVISOR ?X ?Z)
the job of x is in d and the supervisor of x is z--
我们实际想要把这一大堆东西
what we in effect want to do is take this whole mess
用一个盒子封装起来
and draw a box around it
然后把这个盒子里的所有东西
and say this whole thing inside the box
认为是(BOSS ?Z ?D)
is boss of z in division d.
这是我们想要达到的效果
That's in effect what we want to do.
因此 比如说
So, for instance,
我们这样做了过后
if we've done that,
我们想要检查
and we want to check whether or not it's true
Ben Bitdiddle是否为计算机分部的BOSS
that Ben Bitdiddle is a boss in the computer division,
如果我想查询 (BOSS (BITDIDDLE BEN) COMPUTER)
so if I want to say boss of Ben Bitdiddle in the computer division,
想象一下把这条查询输入系统
imagine typing that in as query to the system,
实际上发生的是
in effect what we want to do
在这里先构建一本字典
is set up a dictionary here,
其中 Z=BITDIDDLE
which has z to Ben Bitdiddle
D=COMPUTER
and d to computer.
这个字典又是来自于哪里呢？
Where did that dictionary come from?
我们来看下幻灯片
Let's look at the slide for one second.
这本字典是通过把
That dictionary came from matching the query
查询(BOSS (BITDIDDLE BEN) COMPUTER)
that said boss of Ben Bitdiddle and computer
与规则的结论(BOSS ?Z ?D)相匹配得到
onto the conclusion of the rule: boss of z and d.
所以我们把规则的结论和查询匹配了起来
So we match the query to the conclusion of the rule.
这样我们就获得了一本字典
That gives us a dictionary,
现在我们就要把这本字典输入到这整个结构中
and that's the thing that we would now like to put into this whole big thing
进行处理 并观察是否有输出
and process and see if anything comes out the other side.
如果输出了结果 那么查询就为真
If anything comes out, it'll be true.
这是基本的思想
That's the basic idea.
因此 通常来说
So in general,
我们实现规则的方法就是
the way we implement a rule
用规则的结论去匹配
is we match the conclusion of the rule
假设为真的查询
against something we might want to check it's true.
这个过程会产生一本字典
That match gives us a dictionary,
在有了相关字典后
and with respect to that dictionary,
我们来处理规则的体
we process the body of the rule.
基本上就是这样了
Well, that's really all there is,
但还有两个技术点
except for two technical points.
首先就是
The first technical point is that
我也可能有其它的问法
I might have said something else.
比如说
I might have said
查询计算机分部的BOSS
who's the boss in the computer division?
就可以查询 (BOSS ?WHO COMPUTER)
So I might say boss of who in computer division.
这样做了以后
And if I did that,
我真正想要做的
what I would really like to do in effect is not
就是先建立一本字典
is start up this dictionary
其中有一些约束
with a match that sort of says,
比如 D=COMPUTER
well, d is computer
而?Z是任意值
and z is whatever who is.
我们的匹配器不会那么做
And our matcher won't quite do that.
这不是模式和数据的匹配方式
That's not quite matching a pattern against data.
这是在匹配两个模式
It's matching two patterns
并判断它们是否一致
sort of saying are they consistent or not
又是什么使它们不一致
or what ways make them consistent.
换句话说 我们需要的不是一个模式匹配器
In other words, what we need is not quite a pattern matcher,
而是一种更一般性的东西
but something a little bit more general
就是“合一”算法
called a unifier.
“合一”是更为一般化的模式匹配算法
And a unifier is a slight generalization of a pattern matcher.
合一算法接收两条模式
What a unifier does is take two patterns
它考虑的是：可以找到哪些一般性的元素
and say what's the most general thing you can substitute
用来代换模式中的变量
for the variables in those two patterns
使得它俩能够同时满足
to make them satisfy the pattern simultaneously?
让我来举个例子
Let me give you an example.
我有一个含有两个元素的模式：(?X ?X)
If I have the pattern two-element list, which is x and x,
它描述的是一个二元表
so this is I have a two-element list
不管元素具体是什么
where both elements are the same
但两个元素是相同的
and otherwise I don't care what they are,
我把它与另一个模式进行“合一”
and I unify that against the pattern
后者描述的是一个二元表
that says there's a two-element list,
首元素一张由'A、任意值、C构成的表
and the first one is a and something and c
而第二个元素是由'A、'B、任意值构成的表
and the second one is a and b and z,
那么 合一算法能够告诉我
then what the unifier should tell me is,
在生成的字典中
oh yeah, in that dictionary,
?X必须是(A B C)
x has to be a, b, c,
?Y必须为B ?Z必须为C
and y has to be d and z has to be c.
这些是我必须对X、Y以及Z施加的约束
Those are the restrictions I'd have to put on the values of x, y, and z
以便让两个模式合一
to make these two unify,
或者换句话来说 让它匹配这个?X
or in other words, to make this match x
让它匹配这个?X
and make this match x.
合一算法需要能够推断出这些
The unifier should be able to deduce that.
但是合一算法也会遇到复杂的情况
But the unifier may-- there are more complicated things.
我可能会询问一些复杂的查询
I might have said something a little bit more complicated.
比如这是一个二元表
I might have said there's a list with two elements,
其中的元素都是相同的
and they're both the same,
它要与这个模式进行合一
and they should unify against something of this form.
合一算法也要能够从中推断出
And the unifier should be able to deduce from that.
?Y必须为B
Like that y would have to be b. y would have to be b.
因为这两个是一样的
Because these two are the same,
因此?Y就是B
so y's got to be b.
这里 ?V应该为A
And v here would have to be a.
只要?Z和?W取值相同
And z and w can be anything,
它们就可以是任意值
but they have to be the same thing.
?X就应该是(B A ?W) 其中?W为任意值
And x would have to be b, followed by a, followed by whatever w
或者是?Z -- 因为?Z和?W是一致的
or whatever z is, which is the same.
发现了么？ 合一算法需要从这些模式中推断出信息
So you see, the unifier somehow has to deduce things to unify these patterns.
所以你们可能认为 这其中有某种魔法般的推理
So you might think there's some kind of magic deduction going on,
但其实并不是
but there's not.
合一算法基本上只是对模式匹配的小小修改
A unifier is basically a very simple modification of a pattern matcher.
如果你们翻阅教材 就会发现
And if you look in the book, you'll see something like
在模式匹配算法中加入了三到四行代码
like three or four lines of code added to the pattern matcher you just saw
来处理对称的情况
to handle the symmetric case.
还记得吗？模式匹配中有一处代码判断
Remember, the pattern matcher has a place where it says
这个变量匹配一个常量吗？
is this variable matching a constant.
如果是的话 就在字典中进行检查
And if so, it checks in the dictionary.
在合一算法中只有另一条子句
There's only one other clause in the unifier,
它判断两个变量是否相匹配
which says is this variable matching a variable,
这种情况下你去查询字典
in which case you go look in the dictionary
看它们在字典的约束下是否一致
and see if that's consistent with what's in the dictionary.
因此 这门语言中的所有“推断”
So all the, quote, deduction that's in this language,
你会发现它蕴含在规则应用中
if you sort of look at it, sort of sits in the rule applications,
更进一步地考察 你会发现在合一算法中
which, if you look at that, sits in the unifier,
如果更进一步地用“显微镜”观察
which, if you look at that under a microscope,
基本上就在模式匹配算法中
sits essentially in the pattern matcher.
这其中并没有什么魔法
There's no magic at all going on in there.
而你们所见到的“推断”
And the, quote, deduction that you see
只是因为其中的递归
is just the fact that there's this recursion,
它一点一点地回绕MATCH过程
which is unwinding the matches bit by bit.
它让这个过程看起来很聪明
So it looks like this thing is being very clever,
但它实际上并不是那么聪明
but in fact, it's not being very clever at all.
当然 合一算法需要聪明地识别出一些情况
There are cases where a unifier might have to be clever.
我来举个例子吧
Let me show you one more.
假设我想要用一个二元表进行合一
Suppose I want to unify a list of two elements,
(?X ?X)
x and x,
另一个模式则是 (?Y (a . ?Y))
with a thing that says it's y followed by a dot y.
现在 如果你想一想它所表达的意思
Now, if you think of what that would have to mean,
它表示了?X应该跟?Y一致
it would have to mean that x had better be the same as y,
同时呢
but also
?X又应该跟(A . ?Y)相同
x had better be the same as a list whose first element is a and whose rest is y.
如果你自习思考它成立的条件
And if you think about what that would have to mean,
你会发现 ?Y必须是一个由A构成的无穷表
it would have to mean that y is the infinite list of a's.
从某种角度来说
In some sense,
为了完成这样的合一
in order to do that unification,
我需要求解一个不动点方程
I have to solve the fixed-point equation
(CONS 'A Y)=Y
cons of a to y is equal to y.
通常来说 --- 我这个例子很简单
And in general, I wrote a very simple one.
但实际进行合一时
Really doing unification
我们可能要求解一个任意的不动点方程
might have to solve an arbitrary fixed-point equation:
(F Y)=Y
f of y equals y.
你基本上不能保证
And basically, you can't do that
总能够找到有限的解
and make the thing finite all the time.
我们的逻辑语言又该如何处理这类情况呢？
So how does the logic language handle that?
答案就是：“不处理”
The answer is it doesn't.
#TBD
It just punts.
合一算法中有一处小检查
And there's a little check in the unifier,
用来判断是否为困难的情况
which says, oh, is this one of the hard cases
也就是 匹配这些东西需要求解不动点方程
which when I go to match things would involve solving a fixed-point equation?
遇到这类情况 我就撒手不干
And in this case, I will throw up my hands.
如果不进行这样的检查
And if that check were not in there,
会发生什么情况？
what would happen?
大多数情况就是
In most cases is
合一算法会陷入无穷循环
that the unifier would just go into an infinite loop.
其它的逻辑语言有类似的工作原理
And other logic programming languages work like that.
因此这其中没有什么魔法
So there's really no magic.
简单的情况由匹配器完成
The easy case is done in a matcher.
困难的情况根本不去处理
The hard case is not done at all.
这就是这种技术的现状
And that's about the state of this technology.
现在 我来形式化地描述一下
OK, Let me just say again formally
规则系统的运行原理 -- 也就是合一算法
how rules work now that I talked about unifiers.
因此 正式的定义就是
So the official definition
应用一条规则
is that to apply a rule,
我们需要使用一些之前的术语
we-- well, let's start using some words we've used before.
#TBD
Let's talk about sticking dictionaries into
these big boxes of query things
#TBD
as evaluating these large queries
relative to an environment or a frame.
因此 当我们谈及“字典”的时候
So when you think of that dictionary,
“字典”究竟是什么？
what's the dictionary after all?
它是符号的一系列语义
It's a bunch of meanings for symbols.
我们把它叫做“框架”或者“环境”
That's what we've been calling frames or environments.
根据环境进行操作 又是什么？
What does it mean to do some processing relevant to an environment?
我们把这个叫做“求值”
That's what we've been calling evaluation.
因此我们就说 应用一条规则的方法是
So we can say the way that you apply a rule
先通过将给定的查询与规则的结论合一 得到环境
is to evaluate the rule body relative to an environment
在再该环境中求值相应规则的体
that's formed by unifying the rule conclusion with the given query.
我想要让你们注意的是
And the thing I want you to notice
这非常像是
is the complete formal similarity
元循环求值器以及代换模型
to the net of circular evaluator or the substitution model.
规则的应用就是
To apply a procedure,
在一个环境中求值规则的体
we evaluate the procedure body relative to an environment
环境是通过将实际参数与形式参数绑定起来得到的
that's formed by blinding the procedure parameters to the arguments.
规则、规则的应用、过程的应用
There's a complete formal similarity there
它们在形式上完全相似
between the rules, rule application, and procedure application
尽管它们又非常不同
even though these things are very, very different.
再一次地出现了EVAL-APPLY循环
And again, you have the EVAL APPLY loop.
EVAL-APPLY
EVAL and APPLY.
因此通常来说 我们可能会处理一些复合表达式
So in general, I might be processing some combined expression
它们会变成规则的应用
that will turn into a rule application,
进一步又会产生字典、框架或者环境
which will generate some dictionaries or frames or environments--
不管你要怎么叫它
whatever you want to call them-- from match,
它们随后又会作为某个大的复合对象的输入
which will then be the input to some big compound thing like this.
这有它的一部分 并可能有其它规则的应用
This has pieces of it and may have other rule applications.
这基本上就是相同的循环
And you have essentially the same cycle
尽管这里没有什么东西看起来像过程
even though there's nothing here at all that looks like procedures.
这是因为我们创建的语言
It really has to do with the fact you've built a language
它们的组合手段和抽象手段以某种方式展开
whose means of combination and abstraction unwind in certain ways.
通常来说
And then in general,
最顶层所发生的是
what happens at the very top level,
数据库中也有一些规则
you might have rules in your database also,
数据库中的数据也可能是规则
so things in this database might be rules.
它们用来检查对象是否为真
There are ways to check that things are true.
所以这里可能会有规则检查
So it might come in here and have to do a rule check.
然后就会有一些控制结构
And then there's some control structure
用来判断你访问的是规则
which says, well, you look at some rules, and you look at some data elements,
还是数据元素
and you look at some rules and data elements,
然后不断地把它们扇出来开
and these fan out and out and out.
所以基本上不可能说清楚
So it becomes essentially impossible
是用什么样的顺序来查询这些东西的
to say what order it's looking at these things in,
是广度优先还是深度优先
whether it's breadth first or depth first or anything.
另外一个原因是
And it's even more impossible
我们通过惰性流隐藏了实际执行顺序
because the actual order is somehow buried in the delays of the streams.
因此很难说清楚它的扫描顺序
So what's very hard to tell from this is the order in which it's scanned.
But what's true, because you're looking at the stream view, is that all of them eventually get looked at.
Let me just mention one tiny technical problem.
Suppose I tried saying boss of y is computer, then a funny thing would happen.
As I stuck a dictionary with y in here, I might get-- this y is not the same as that y, which was the other piece of somebody's job description.
So if I really only did literally what I said, we'd get some variable conflict problems. So I lied to you a little bit.
Notice that problem is exactly a problem we've run into before.
It is precisely the need for local variables in a language.
When I have the sum of squares, that x had better not be that x.
That's exactly the same as this y had better not be that y.
And we know how to solve that.
That was this whole environment model, and we built chains of frames and all sorts of things like that.
There's a much more brutal way to solve it.
In the query language, we didn't even do that.
We did something completely brutal.
We said every time you apply a rule, rename consistently all the variables in the rule to some new unique names that won't conflict with anything.
That's conceptually simpler, but really brutal and not particularly efficient.
But notice, we could have gotten rid of all of our environment structures if we defined for procedures in Lisp the same thing.
If every time we applied a procedure and did the substitution model we renamed all the variables in the procedure, then we never would have had to worry about local variables because they would never arise.
OK, well, that would be inefficient, and it's inefficient here in the query language, too, but we did it to keep it simple.
Let's break for questions.
AUDIENCE: When you started this section, you emphasized how powerful our APPLY EVAL model was that we could use it for any language.
And then you say we're going to have this language which is so different.
It turns out that this language, as you just pointed out, is very much the same.
I'm wondering if you're arguing that all languages end up coming down to this you can apply a rule or apply a procedure or some kind of apply?
PROFESSOR: I would say that pretty much any language where you really are building up these means of combination and giving them simpler names and you're saying anything of the sort, like here's a general kind of expression, like how to square something, almost anything that you would call a procedure.
If that's got to have parts, you have to unwind those parts.
You have to have some kind of organization which says when I look at the abstract variables or tags or whatever you want to call them that might stand for particular things, you have to keep track of that, and that's going to be something like an environment.
And then if you say this part can have parts which I have to unwind, you've got to have something like this cycle.
And lots and lots of languages have that character when they sort of get put together in this way.
This language again really is different because there's nothing like procedures on the outside.
When you go below the surface and you see the implementation, of course, it starts looking the same.
But from the outside, it's a very different world view.
You're not computing functions of inputs.
AUDIENCE: You mentioned earlier that when you build all of these rules in pattern matcher and with the delayed action of streams, you really have no way to know in what order things are evaluated.
PROFESSOR: Right.
AUDIENCE: And that would indicate then that you should only express declarative knowledge that's true for all-time, no-time sequence built into it.
Otherwise, these things get all-- PROFESSOR: Yes.
Yes.
The question is this really is set up for doing declarative knowledge, and as I presented it-- and I'll show you some of the ugly warts under this after the break.
As I presented it, it's just doing logic.
And in principle, if it were logic, it wouldn't matter what order it's getting done.
And it's quite true when you start doing things where you have side effects like adding things to the database and taking things out, and we'll see some others, you use that kind of control.
So, for example, contrasting with Prolog.
Say Prolog has various features where you really exploit the order of evaluation.
And people write Prolog programs that way.
That turns out to be very complicated in Prolog, although if you're an expert Prolog programmer, you can do it.
However, here I don't think you can do it at all.
It's very complicated because you really are giving up control over any prearranged order of trying things.
AUDIENCE: Now, that would indicate then that you have a functional mapping.
And when you started out this lecture, you said that we express the declarative knowledge which is a relation, and we don't talk about the inputs and the outputs.
PROFESSOR: Well, there's a pun on functional, right?
There's function in the sense of no side effects and not depending on what order is going on.
And then there's functional in the sense of mathematical function, which means input and output.
And it's just that pun that you're making, I think.
AUDIENCE: I'm a little unclear on what you're doing with these two statements, the two boss statements.
Is the first one building up the database and the second one a query or-- PROFESSOR: OK, I'm sorry.
What I meant here, if I type something like this in as a query-- I should have given an example way at the very beginning.
If I type in job, Ben Bitdiddle, computer wizard, what the processing will do is if it finds a match, it'll find a match to that exact thing, and it'll type out a job, Ben Bitdiddle, computer wizard.
If it doesn't find a match, it won't find anything.
So what I should have said is the way you use the query language to check whether something is true, remember, that's one of the things you want to do in logic programming, is you type in your query and either that comes out or it doesn't.
So what I was trying to illustrate here, I wanted to start with a very simple example before talking about unifiers.
So what I should have said, if I just wanted to check whether this is true, I could type that in and see if anything came out AUDIENCE: And then the second one-- PROFESSOR: The second one would be a real query.
AUDIENCE: A real query, yeah.
PROFESSOR: What would come out, see, it would go in here say with FOO, and in would go frame that says z is bound to who and d is bound to computer.
And this will pass through, and then by the time it got out of here, who would pick up a binding.
AUDIENCE: On the unifying thing there, I still am not sure what happens with who and z.
If the unifying-- the rule here says--  OK, so you say that you can't make question mark equal to question mark who.
PROFESSOR: Right.
That's what the matcher can't do.
But what this will mean to a unifier is that there's an environment with three variables.
d here is computer.
z is whatever who is.
So if later on in the matcher routine it said, for example, who has to be 3, then when I looked up in the dictionary, it will say, oh, z is 3 because it's the same as who.
And that's in some sense the only thing you need to do to extend the unifier to a matcher.
AUDIENCE: OK, because it looked like when you were telling how to unify it, it looked like you would put the things together in such a way that you'd actually solve and have a value for both of them.
And what it looks like now is that you're actually pass a dictionary with two variables and the variables are linked.
PROFESSOR: Right.
It only looks like you're solving for both of them because you're sort of looking at the whole solution at once.
If you sort of watch the thing getting built up recursively, it's merely this.
AUDIENCE: OK, so you do pass off that dictionary with two variables?
PROFESSOR: That's right.
AUDIENCE: And link?
PROFESSOR: Right. It just looks like an ordinary dictionary.
AUDIENCE: When you're talking about the unifier, is it that there are some cases or some points that you are not able to use by them?
PROFESSOR: Right.
AUDIENCE: Can you just by building the rules or writing the forms know in advance if you are going to be able to solve to get the unification or not?
Can you add some properties either to the rules itself or to the formula that you're writing so that you avoid the problem of not finding unification?
PROFESSOR: I mean, you can agree, I think, to write in a fairly restricted way where you won't run into it.
See, because what you're getting-- see, the place where you get into problems is when you-- well, again, you're trying to match things like that against things where these have structure, where a, y, b, y something.
So this is the kind of place where you're going to get into trouble.
AUDIENCE: So you can do that syntactically?
PROFESSOR: So you can kind of watch your rules in the kinds of things that your writing.
AUDIENCE: So that's the problem that the builder of the database has to be concerned?
PROFESSOR: That's a problem.
It's a problem either-- not quite the builder of the database, the person who is expressing the rules, or the builder of the database.
What the unifier actually does is you can check at the next level down when you actually get to the unifier and you'll see in the code where it looks up in the dictionary.
If it sort of says what does y have to be?
Oh, does y have to be something that contains a y as its expression?
At that point, the unifier and say, oh my God, I'm trying to solve a fixed-point equation.
I'll give it up here.
AUDIENCE: You make the distinction between the rules in the database.
Are the rules added to the database?
PROFESSOR: Yes.
Yes, I should have said that.
One way to think about rules is that they're just other things in the database.
So if you want to check the things that have to be checked in the database, they're kind of virtual facts that are in the database.
AUDIENCE: But in that explanation, you made the differentiation between database and the rules itself.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, I probably should not have done that.
The only reason to do that is in terms of the implementation.
When you look at the implementation, there's a part which says check either primitive assertions in the database or check rules.
And then the real reason why you can't tell what order things are going to come out in and is that the rules database and the data database sort of get merged in a kind of delayed evaluation way.
And so that's what makes the order very complicated.
OK, let's break.
We've just seen how the logic language works and how rules work.
Now, let's turn to a more profound question.
What do these things mean?
That brings us to the subtlest, most devious part of this whole query language business, and that is that it's not quite what it seems to be.
AND and OR and NOT and the logical implication of rules are not really the AND and OR and NOT and logical implication of logic.
Let me give you an example of that.
Certainly, if we have two things in logic, it ought to be the case that AND of P and Q is the same as AND of Q and P and that OR of P and Q is the same as OR of Q and P. But let's look here.
Here's an example.
Let's talk about somebody outranking somebody else in our little database organization.
We'll say s is outranked by b or if either the supervisor of this is b or there's some middle manager here, that supervisor of s is m, and m is outranked by b.
So there's one way to define rule outranked by.
Or we can write exactly the same thing, except at the bottom here, we reversed the order of these two clauses.
And certainly if this were logic, those ought to mean the same thing.
However, in our particular implementation, if you say something like who's outranked by Ben Bitdiddle, what you'll find is that this rule will work perfectly well and generate answers, whereas this rule will go into an infinite loop.
And the reason for that is that this will come in and say, oh, who's outranked by Ben Bitdiddle?
Find an s which is outranked by b, where b is Ben Bitdiddle, which is going to happen in it a subproblem.
Oh gee, find an m such as m is outranked by Ben Bitdiddle with no restrictions on m.
So this will say in order to solve this problem, I solve exactly the same problem.
And then after I've solved that, I'll check for a supervisory relationship.
Whereas this one won't get into that, because before it tries to find this outranked by, it'll already have had a restriction on m here.
So these two things which ought to mean the same, in fact, one goes into an infinite loop.
One does not.
That's a very extreme case of a general thing that you'll find in logic programming that if you start changing the order of the things in the ANDs or ORs, you'll find tremendous differences in efficiency.
And we just saw an infinitely big difference in efficiency and an infinite loop.
And there are similar things having to do with the order in which you enter rules.
The order in which it happens to look at rules in the database may vastly change the efficiency with which it gets out answers or, in fact, send it into an infinite loop for some orderings.
And this whole thing has to do with the fact that you're checking these rules in some order.
And some rules may lead to really long paths of implication.
Others might not.
And you don't know a priori which ones are good and which ones are bad.
And there's a whole bunch of research having to do with that, mostly having to do with thinking about making parallel implementations of logic programming languages.
And in some sense, what you'd like to do is check all rules in parallel and whichever ones get answers, you bubble them up.
And if some go down infinite deductive changed, well, you just-- you know, memory is cheap and processors are cheap, and you just let them buzz for as for as long as you want.
There's a deeper problem, though, in comparing this logic language to real logic.
The example I just showed you, it went into an infinite loop maybe, but at least it didn't give the wrong answer.
There's an actual deeper problem when we start comparing, seriously comparing this logic language with real classical logic.
So let's sort of review real classical logic.
All humans are mortal.
That's pretty classical logic.
Then maybe we'll continue in the very best classical tradition.
We'll say all-- let's make it really classical.
All Greeks are human, which has the syllogism that Socrates is a Greek.
And then what do you write here?
I think three dots, classical logic.
Therefore, then the syllogism, Socrates is mortal.
So there's some real honest classical logic.
Let's compare that with our classical logic database.
So here's a classical logic database.
Socrates is a Greek.
Plato is a Greek.
Zeus is a Greek, and Zeus is a god.
And all humans are mortal.
To show that something is mortal, it's enough to show that it's human.
All humans are fallible.
And all Greeks are humans is not quite right.
This says that all Greeks who are not gods are human.
So to show something's human, it's enough to show it's a Greek and not a god.
And the address of any Greek god is Mount Olympus.
So there's a little classical logic database.
And indeed, that would work fairly well.
If we type that in and say is Socrates mortal or Socrates fallible or mortal?
It'll say yes.
Is Plato mortal and fallible.
If we say is Zeus mortal?
It won't find anything.
And it'll work perfectly well.
However, suppose we want to extend this.
Let's define what it means for someone to be a perfect being.
Let's say rule: a perfect being.
And I think this is right.
If you're up on your medieval scholastic philosophy, I believe that perfect beings are ones who were neither mortal nor fallible.
AND NOT mortal x, NOT fallible x.
So we'll define this system to teach it what a perfect being is.
And now what we're going to do is he ask for the address of all the perfect beings.
AND the address of x is y and x is perfect.
And so what we're generating here is the world's most exclusive mailing list. For the address of all the perfect things, we might have typed this in.
Or we might type in this.
We'll say AND perfect of x and the address of x is y.
Well, suppose we type all that in and we try this query.
This query is going to give us an answer.
This query will say, yeah, Mount Olympus.
This query, in fact, is going to give us nothing.
It will say no addresses of perfect beings.
Now, why is that?
Why is there a difference?
This is not an infinite loop question.
This is a different answer question.
The reason is that if you remember the implementation of NOT, NOT acted as a filter.
NOT said I'm going to take some possible dictionaries, some possible frames, some possible answers, and filter out the ones that happened to satisfy some condition, and that's how I implement NOT.
If you think about what's going on here, I'll build this query box where the output of an address piece gets fed into a perfect piece.
What will happen is the address piece will set up some things of everyone whose address I know.
Those will get filtered by the NOTs inside perfect here.
So it will throw out the ones which happened to be either mortal or fallible.
In the other order what happens is I set this up, started up with an empty frame.
The perfect in here doesn't find anything for the NOTs to filter, so nothing comes out here at all.
And there's sort of nothing there that gets fed into the address thing.
So here, I don't get an answer.
And again, the reason for that is NOT isn't generating anything.
NOT's only throwing out things.
And if I never started up with anything, there's nothing for it to throw out.
So out of this thing, I get the wrong answer.
How can you fix that?
Well, there are ways to fix that.
So you might say, well, that's sort of stupid.
Why are you just doing all your NOT stuff at the beginning?
The right way to implement NOT is to realize that when you have conditions like NOT, you should generate all your answers first, and then with each of these dictionaries pass along until at the very end I'll do filtering.
And there are implementations of logic languages that work like that that solve this particular problem.
However, there's a more profound problem, which is which one of these is the right answer?
Is it Mount Olympus or is it nothing?
So you might say it's Mount Olympus, because after all, Zeus is in that database, and Zeus was neither mortal nor fallible.
So you might say Zeus wants to satisfy NOT mortal Zeus or NOT fallible Zeus.
But let's actually look at that database.
Let's look at it.
There's no way-- how does it know that Zeus is not fallible?
There's nothing in there about that.
What's in there is that humans are fallible.
How does it know that Zeus is not mortal?
There's nothing in there about that.
It just said I don't have any rule, which-- the only way I can deduce something's mortal is if it's human, and that's all it really knows about mortal.
And in fact, if you remember your classical mythology, you know that the Greek gods were not mortal but fallible.
So the answer is not in the rules there.
See, why does it deduce that?
See, Socrates would certainly not have made this error of logic.
What NOT needs in this language is not NOT.
It's not the NOT of logic.
What NOT needs in this language is not deducible from things in the database as opposed to not true.
That's a very big difference.
Subtle, but big.
So, in fact, this is perfectly happy to say not anything that it doesn't know about.
So if you ask it is it not true that Zeus likes chocolate ice cream?
It will say sure, it's not true.
Or anything else or anything it doesn't know about.
NOT means not deducible from the things you've told me.
In a world where you're identifying not deducible with, in fact, not true, this is called the closed world assumption.
The closed world assumption.
Anything that I cannot deduce from what I know is not true, right?
If I don't know anything about x, the x isn't true.
That's very dangerous.
From a logical point of view, first of all, it doesn't really makes sense.
Because if I don't know anything about x, I'm willing to say not x.
But am I willing to say not not x?
Well, sure, I don't know anything about that either maybe.
So not not x is not necessarily the same as x and so on and so on and so on, so there's some sort of funny bias in there.
So that's sort of funny.
The second thing, if you start building up real reasoning programs based on this, think how dangerous that is.
You're saying I know I'm in a position to deduce everything true that's relevant to this problem.
I'm reasoning, and built into my reasoning mechanism is the assumption that anything that I don't know can't possibly be relevant to this problem, right?
There are a lot of big organizations that work like that, right?
Most corporate marketing divisions work like that.
You know the consequences to that.
So it's very dangerous to start really typing in these big logical implication systems and going on what they say, because they have this really limiting assumption built in.
So you have to be very, very careful about that.
And that's a deep problem.
That's not a problem about we can make a little bit cleverer implementation and do the filters and organize the infinite loops to make them go away.
It's a different kind of problem.
It's a different semantics.
So I think to wrap this up, it's fair to say that logic programming I think is a terrifically exciting idea, the idea that you can bridge this gap from the imperative to the declarative, that you can start talking about relations and really get tremendous power by going above the abstraction of what's my input and what's my output.
And linked to logic, the problem is it's a goal that I think has yet to be realized.
And probably one of the very most interesting research questions going on now in languages is how do you somehow make a real logic language?
And secondly, how do you bridge the gap from this world of logic and relations to the worlds of more traditional languages and somehow combine the power of both.
OK, let's break.
AUDIENCE: Couldn't you solve that last problem by having the extra rules that imply it?
The problem here is you have the definition of something, but you don't have the definition of its opposite.
If you include in the database something that says something implies mortal x, something else implies not mortal x, haven't you basically solved the problem?
PROFESSOR: But the issue is do you put a finite number of those in?
AUDIENCE: If things are specified always in pairs-- PROFESSOR: But the impression is then what do you do about deduction?
You can't specify NOTs.
But the problem is, in a big system, it turns out that might not be a finite number of things.
There are also sort of two issues.
Partly it might not be finite.
Partly it might be that's not what you want.
So a good example would be suppose I want to do connectivity.
I want a reason about connectivity.
And I'm going to tell you there's four things: a and b and c and d.
And I'll tell you a is connected to b and c's connected to d.
And now I'll tell you is a connected to d?
That's the question.
There's an example where I would like something like the closed world assumption.
That's a tiny toy, but a lot of times, I want to be able to say something like anything that I haven't told you, assume is not true.
So it's not as simple as you only want to put in explicit NOTs all over the place.
It's that sometimes it really isn't clear what you even want.
That having to specify both everything and not everything is too precise, and then you get down into problems there.
But there are a lot of approaches that explicitly put in NOTs and reason based on that.
So it's a very good idea.
It's just that then it starts becoming a little cumbersome in the very large problems you'd like to use.
AUDIENCE: I'm not sure how directly related to the argument this is, but one of your points was that one of the dangers of the closed rule is you never really know all the things that are there.
You never really know all the parts to it.
Isn't that a major problem with any programming?
I always write programs where I assume that I've got all the cases, and so I check for them all or whatever, and somewhere down the road, I find out that I didn't check for one of them.
PROFESSOR: Well, sure, it's true.
But the problem here is it's that assumption which is the thing that you're making if you believe you're identifying this with logic.
So you're quite right.
It's a situation you're never in.
The problem is if you're starting to believe that what this is doing is logic and you look at the rules you write down and say what can I deduce from them, you have to be very careful to remember that NOT means something else.
And it means something else based on an assumption which is probably not true.
AUDIENCE: Do I understand you correctly that you cannot fix this problem without killing off all possibilities of inference through altering NOT?
PROFESSOR: No, that's not quite right.
There are other--  there are ways to do logic with real NOTs.
There are actually ways to do that.
But they're very inefficient as far as anybody knows.
And they're much more--  the, quote, inference in here is built into this unifier and this pattern matching unification algorithm.
There are ways to automate real logical reasoning.
But it's not based on that, and logic programming languages don't tend to do that because it's very inefficient as far as anybody knows.
All right, thank you.